Jack Rasmussen Gallery Records, 1936-1984, bulk 1978-1982, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Jack Rasmussen Gallery records
1936-1984
bulk 1978-1982
Archives of American Art
Jack Rasmussen Gallery (Washington, D.C.)
AAA.jackrasm
Archival Resource Key
8.3 Linear feet
The Jack Rasmussen Gallery records measure 8.3 linear feet and date from 1936 to 1984, with the bulk of the records dating from 1978 to 1982. The records shed light on the Washington, DC gallery's operations through administrative records, financial and legal records, artist files, and printed material.
Biographical / Historical
The Jack Rasmussen Gallery was established in 1978 in Washington, D.C. by painter and art dealer Jack Rasmussen. The gallery's first show was an exhibition of paintings by artist Reginald Pollack. Rasmussen Gallery went on to exhibit contemporary painters, sculptors, and audiovisual artists, many of whome were from the D.C. area. Artists exhibited at the gallery include Annie Gawlak, Robert Gates, Tom Green, Sy Gresser, Taro Ichihashi, Walter Kravitz, and Reginald Pollack. Rasmussen closed the gallery in 1983.
Jack Rasmussen began his career in 1975 as assistant director of the Washington Project for the Arts under its founder Alice Denney. After closing the gallery, Rasmussen helped launch the Rockville Arts Place program in Rockville, Maryland, and then served as executive director of Maryland Art Place in Baltimore, Maryland for 10 years. Rasmussen served as director of di Rosa Center for Contemporary Art in Napa, California, and has served as Director and Curator of the American University Museum at the Katzen Arts Center, Washington, DC, since it opened in 2005.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as four series.
Series 1: Administrative Records, 1976-1984 (Box 1-3; 2.6 linear feet)
Series 2: Artist Files, 1936-1983, bulk 1978-1982 (Box 3-6; 3.5 linear feet)
Series 3: Financial and Legal Records, 1978-1983 (Box 6-9; 1.7 linear feet)
Series 4: Printed Material, 1978-1982 (Box 8-9; .5 linear feet)
Scope and Contents
The Jack Rasmussen Gallery records measure 8.3 linear feet and date from 1936 to 1984, with the bulk of the records dating from 1978 to 1982. The records shed light on the gallery's operations through administrative records, financial and legal records, artist files, and printed material.
Administrative records consist of files related to art organizations, several of the gallery's exhibitions, collectors, and Jack Rasmussen's career. Files include correspondence, an interview with Rasmussen conducted by Robert Bove, price lists, by- laws, guestbooks, memos, writings, and some sales records. Artist files are comprised of correspondence, exhibition announcements, price lists, slides and photographs of artwork and artists, sales records, statements, and agreements. Some newspaper clippings, sketches and illustrations, and loan agreements are also present. Financial and legal records consist of contracts, sales records, account ledgers, bills, invoices, and stationery. Printed materials include press releases, exhibition announcements, posters, and catalogs, newspaper and magazine clippings, and a couple of scrapbooks.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated in 1982 and 1997 by Jack Rasmussen.
Interviews; Art galleries, Commercial -- Washington (D.C.); Rasmussen, Jack
- Administrative Records, 1976-1984; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 2.6 Linear feet Box 1-3
  Scope and Contents
  Files in this series cover a variety of subjects, including exhibitions held at the gallery and elsewhere; involvement by Jack Rasmussen and his gallery in art organizations and institutions; donations; and publicity. Found in these files are correspondence, price lists, loan records, newspaper and magazine clippings, writings, artist resumes, and organizational records such as meeting minutes, memos, and by laws. General correspondence files consist of letters with artists, collectors, museums, and also include some sales records. A significant portion of this series is comprised of Patron/Artist cards that contain artist and collector contact information, prices, and some sales records.
  This series also includes several files relating to the personal and professional life of Jack Rasmussen. These files consist of writings and a notepad; an interview transcript; correspondence with artists, colleagues, and friends; postcards; photographs from events; and scant appraisal records.
  - Advertising, 1979-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Building and Property, 1980-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - CityArt 1981, 1979-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1979-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Corcoran Gallery and School of Art, 1980-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Denney, Alice, 1978-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Designer, Marc Meadows, 1980-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Donations, 1976-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Exhibitions, Group Show 1980-1982, Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9-11)
  - Exhibitions, Guest Books, 1978-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12-18)
  - Framing, 1979-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Gallery Owners at Home, 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Guest Informant, 1980-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Internships, 1978-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Landsburgh Department Store, Washington, D.C., 1978-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Mailing List, 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Montgomery College Art Gallery, 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Museum of Temporary Art, 1980-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Museums, 1978-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Patron and Artist Cards, circa 1978-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2-10)
  - Patron and Artist Cards, circa 1978-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - Photographs, Miscellaneous, 1978, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Rapoport, Sheldon, 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Rasmussen, Jack, "Artist Survival Manual", 1978-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 5-6)
  - Rasmussen, Jack, Interviewed by Robert Bove, 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Rasmussen, Jack, Notepad, circa 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Rasmussen, Jack, Personal and Professional Papers, 1978-1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 9-10)
  - Rasmussen, John A., "Access to Exhibition Space", undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Rosenthal, Benjamin, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Washington Art Dealers Association, 1981-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Washington Project for the Arts, 1974-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - White House, 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Workshops, Symposiums, and Happenings, 1979-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Artist Files, 1936-1983; bulk 1978-1982; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 3.5 Linear feet Box 3-6
  Folders typically include correspondence, exhibition announcements, price lists, slides and photographs of artwork and artists, sales records, statements, and agreements. Some artist files also include images of exhibitions, illustrated letters and sketches, and loan agreements.
  - Ayoroa, Rudy, 1977-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Barnes, Mary, 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Blee, John, 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Bodnarchuk, Raya, 1980-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Burns, Terry, 1981, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Canas, Benjamin, 1977-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Clark, Lucy, 1974-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Davidov, Corinne, 1980-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Davis, Douglas, 1979-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Dendler, Royce, 1979-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Dendler, Royce, 1978-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Dutter, Bill, 1979-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Firestone, Susan, 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Frisbee, Phil, 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Fullerton, Paul, 1978-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Gair, Sondra, 1981-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Gardner, Chris, 1980-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Gates, Robert, 1936, 1978-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 8-10)
  - Gawlak, Annie, 1975, 1979-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 11-12)
  - Goldblatt, Joel, 1971-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Grady, Ruby, 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Green, Tom, 1978-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 15-16)
  - Gresser, Sy, 1974-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 17-18)
  - Haid, Nan, 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Haner, Lee, Papers relating to Common Sense: A Proposal for Franctional Currency by Lee E. Haner (1981), 1981-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Harmon, Hank and Lee, 1978-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Haynie, Ron, 1978-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Herzbrun, Helene McKinsey, 1978-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Ichihashi, Taro, 1979-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Jacobs, Herald, 1978-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Kamen, Robert, 1978-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Kaplowitz, Laurie, 1978-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Keesing, Madeleine, 1980-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Kelly, Ed, 1978-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Kravitz, Walter, 1979-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 3-4)
  - Kremgold, David, 1976-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Kruvant, Steve, 1978-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Kuhne, Dan, 1980-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - La Rouche, Marianne, 1977-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Laureano, Roberto, 1979-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Levy, Pamela, 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Lundin, Norman, 1978-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Mehutan, Hava, 1978-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Montgomery, Nan, 1981-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Moran, Doug, 1976-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Ostovani, Farhad, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Palmer, Nancy Hetenyi, 1977-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Pollack, Reginald, 1976-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 17-19)
  - Pollack, Reginald, The Seasons (1981), 1980-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Romano, Jaime, 1977-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Shaffer, Mike, 1978-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Shannon, Joe, 1980-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Signature, Cynthia, "The Book of Suicide", 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Staton, David, 1979-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Stoddard, Ann, 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Sundquist, Jim, 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Velez, Maria, 1980-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Walker, Sandy, 1978-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Weisel, Mindy, 1978-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 7-9)
  - Willis, Bill, 1981-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Young, Phil, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Zerne, Ed, 1979-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Artists, Mixed Papers, 1978-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 12-15)
  - Artists, Resumes, circa 1978-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 16-17)
  - Artists, Slides to be Returned, circa 1978-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 18-19)
- Financial and Legal Records, 1978-1983; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 1.7 Linear feet Box 6-9
  Financial records consist of gallery and artist account ledgers and statements, sales slips, bills, and invoices. Also present are sheets of sales form stationery. Legal records shed light on the gallery's partnership program through contracts, inventories, and correspondence; and also include drafts and blank copies of artist agreements.
  - Account Ledgers, 1980-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 20-21)
  - Agreement and Promissory Notes, 1979-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Artist Accounts, 1979-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Artist Accounts, 1979-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Artist Agreements, 1978-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Artist Financial Statements, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Asset and Liability Statements, 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Bank Statements, 1978-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Bills, Thomas More Associates, 1980-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Bills, Art Transportation, 1979-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Bills, Quicksilver Photographers, 1981-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Bills, 1978-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Cash Disbursement Journal, 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Checkbook Balance Slips, 1978-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 10-12)
  - Checks and Deposit Slips, 1978-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 13-17)
  - Gallery Insurance, 1978-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Invoices and Sales Records, 1978-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Ledger Books, 1978-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Limited Partnerships, Agreements, 1979-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Limited Partnership, Income Tax, 1979-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Loans, 1977, 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Sales Records, Purchase Slips, 1978-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 6-7)
  - Stationery, Sales Form, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Printed Material, 1978-1982; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet Box 8-9
  Found here are press releases; two scrapbooks comprised of newspaper clippings, exhibition announcements, and catalogs; and loose clippings related to Jack Rasmussen, his gallery, and general art- and business-related topics. Also present are a handful of exhibition posters, exhibition announcements for a majority of Rasmussen's shows, and exhibition catalogs from the solo shows of Farhad Ostovani, Havana Mehutan, John Blee, and Robert Gates.
  - Rasmussen Gallery, Announcements, 1978-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 9-11)
  - Rasmussen Gallery, Calendar, 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Rasmussen Gallery, Exhibition Catalogs, 1979-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Rasmussen Gallery, Exhibition Posters, 1978-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 13-14)
  - Rasmussen Gallery, Press Releases, 1978-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Rasmussen Gallery, Newspaper and Magazine Clippings, 1979-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Rasmussen Gallery, Scrapbook, 1978-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Rasmussen Gallery, Scrapbook, 1978-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - "Forty Eight Pages: Line", 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Soho Baroque Opera, Event Program, 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous Clippings and Publications, 1978-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 6)